<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>conference | Aman Bagrecha</title>
    <link>https://amanbagrecha.github.io/tag/conference/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://amanbagrecha.github.io/tag/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>conference</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 12:04:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://amanbagrecha.github.io/media/icon_hub8f2c4a40c112e5edee4297ae1d00aa4_198578_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>conference</title>
      <link>https://amanbagrecha.github.io/tag/conference/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first FOSS4G experience</title>
      <link>https://amanbagrecha.github.io/post/event/my-first-foss4g/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 12:04:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://amanbagrecha.github.io/post/event/my-first-foss4g/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I embarked on a journey to attend the esteemed geospatial conference, FOSS4G 2023, held in Prizren. As I reflect, it was an event that left a profound impact on me, and I want to treasure these memories forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/amanbagrecha/amanbagrecha.github.io/assets/76432265/6361e093-e11b-4c4c-b7dc-e0b293f515b0&#34; alt=&#34;WhatsApp Image 2023-07-06 at 01 39 40&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption align = &#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Day1: Entering the Exhibition center at ITP, Prizren&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a couple of months ago, I had my doubts about attending FOSS4G, as I had never traveled to a foreign country before and the host country was not very well known. The logistics to get visa and planning the round-trip seemed daunting, and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure if it would be worth the investment and energy. However, to my delight, I discovered that there were other indians planning their travel too, making the planning process much smoother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there I was, hopping on the plane to Pristina, Kosovo, and thinking to myself, &amp;ldquo;Did I really make the right call by shelling out a ton of money for this conference?&amp;rdquo; But, looking back now, I have to say, it was totally worth it! All the energy and effort I put into being a part of this event, it paid off big time. I&amp;rsquo;m filled with a sense of contentment right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my time at foss4g, I got to hang out with the cool, nerdy core developers, authors, organizers, professors, and users of geospatial technology.  I made some awesome new friends and dove headfirst into the wild nightlife of that stunning city. The experience was overwhelming, and it demanded an extra surge of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With dense knowledge delivered within every conference room, I had to decide to let go one talk over another. Thankfully the talks are recorded, and will be shared freely and openly, adhering the spirit of foss4g!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/amanbagrecha/amanbagrecha.github.io/assets/76432265/adf68f3c-277c-439c-9fe1-e551d2e4341e&#34; alt=&#34;WhatsApp Image 2023-07-06 at 00 21 58 (4)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption align = &#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Day5: Presenting my work to a room full of geonerds&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only was this my first foss4g, but also the first time I presented my work. I was thrilled to receive positive feedback after my talk and to connect with individuals who shared my passion and interests. It was like finding my tribe!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These ten days in Kosovo were one of the most remarkable days of my life. The local people I met, both from Kosovo and Albania, made me feel right at home and added to the incredible experience. I&amp;rsquo;m back home, with a fresh perspective on life, a bunch of goals to accomplish, and a trove of memories that I will cherish forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/amanbagrecha/store-info/assets/76432265/e391ae8c-fdae-4435-971b-a90d585143c7&#34; alt=&#34;WhatsApp Image 2023-07-06 at 16 54 10&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption align = &#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Random day: City tour with friends&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little did I know, a &amp;ldquo;mere&amp;rdquo; conference could dive deep into technical know-how, forge bonds for a lifetime, question my views on status quo, understand cultural differences, and also make me feel blessed to be part of this community!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cannot fathom the sheer knowledge I gained during these 10 days! From learning about state of the art innovation in geospatial, to learning life lessons to think beyond technology! I hope to have the opportunity to attend again next year and reunite with the friends I made along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you foss4g community, the people of Kosovo and to the organizers who made this extraordinary event possible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fingers crossed, hope to meet again next year in Brazil!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS: This post is a glimpse of what transpired during the conference! Highly encourage everybody to attend this event and experience it yourself!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/amanbagrecha/amanbagrecha.github.io/assets/76432265/60ab5cd6-4697-4b5d-990a-791406d6ea65&#34; alt=&#34;WhatsApp Image 2023-07-06 at 01 03 35&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption align = &#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Everyday visit: Stunning landscape of Prizren city, Kosovo&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
